The global economic financial crisis has reignited public interest
جدّدت الأزمة الاقتصاديّة العالميّة الأخيرة اهتمام الرّأي العامّ
in something that's actually one of the oldest questions in economics,
بسؤال يعدّ من أقدم الأسئلة في علوم الاقتصاد،
dating back to at least before Adam Smith.
كان موجودا حتّى قبل آدم سميث.
And that is, why is it that countries with seemingly similar economies and institutions
وهو: لماذا الدّول التي لها مؤسّسات و اقتصاد متشابهة, على ما يظهر
can display radically different savings behavior?
تظهر سلوكات توفيريّة مختلفة جذريّا؟
Now, many brilliant economists have spent their entire lives working on this question,
العديد من خبراء الاقتصاد أمضوا حياتهم كاملة يعملون على هذا السّؤال،
and as a field we've made a tremendous amount of headway
لقد تقدّمنا كثيرا في هذا الميدان،
and we understand a lot about this.
و أصبحنا نعلم الكثير حول هذا الموضوع.
What I'm here to talk with you about today is an intriguing new hypothesis
أنا هنا اليوم لأحدّثكم عن فرضيّة جديدة مثيرة للاهتمام
and some surprisingly powerful new findings that I've been working on
و بعض الاكتشافات الضّخمة التي قمت بالعمل عليها
about the link between the structure of the language you speak
حول الصّلة بين تركيبة اللّغة التي تتكلّمها
and how you find yourself with the propensity to save.
و نزعتك نحو توفير الأموال.
Let me tell you a little bit about savings rates, a little bit about language,
دعوني أخبركم قليلا حول معدّلات الادّخار و قليلا حول اللّغة،
and then I'll draw that connection.
ثمّ سنقوم بربطهما معا.
Let's start by thinking about the member countries of the OECD,
لنبدأ بالتفكّير في الدّول الأعضاء بOECD،
or the Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development.
أو منظمة التّعاون والتّنمية الاقتصادية.
OECD countries, by and large, you should think about these
الدّول المنتمية لمنظمة التّعاون والتّنمية الاقتصادية،
as the richest, most industrialized countries in the world.
هي من أغنى الدّول الصناعيّة في العالم.
And by joining the OECD, they were affirming a common commitment
و بانضمامها للمنظّمة، فهي تؤكّد على التزام جماعيّ
to democracy, open markets and free trade.
بالديمقراطيّة، الأسواق المفتوحة و التّجارة الحرّة.
Despite all of these similarities, we see huge differences in savings behavior.
ورغم كلّ هذه التشابهات، فإنّنا نرى اختلافات كبيرة في السّلوك التوفيريّ.
So all the way over on the left of this graph,
على طول الجزء الأيسر من هذا الرّسم البيانيّ، ما ترونه هو أنّ
what you see is many OECD countries saving over a quarter of their GDP every year,
العديد من الدول المنتمية لهذه المنظّمة توفّر سنويّا قرابة ربع ناتجها الدّاخلي الإجمالي،
and some OECD countries saving over a third of their GDP per year.
و بعض الدّول الآخرى توفّر سنويّا حوالي الثّلث من ناتجها الداخلي الإجمالي.
Holding down the right flank of the OECD, all the way on the other side, is Greece.
من الجهة الأخرى، هناك اليونان.
And what you can see is that over the last 25 years,
يمكنكم أن تروا أنّ على امتداد الـ25 سنة الأخيرة،
Greece has barely managed to save more than 10 percent of their GDP.
وجدت اليونان صعوبة في توفير أكثر من 10% من ناتجها الدّاخلي الإجمالي.
It should be noted, of course, that the United States and the U.K. are the next in line.
نلاحظ أنّ الولايات المتّحدة الأمريكية و المملكة المتّحدة هما التّاليتان بعد اليونان.
Now that we see these huge differences in savings rates,
الآن و بعد اطّلاعنا على هذه الاختلافات الكبيرة في معدّلات التّوفير،
how is it possible that language might have something to do with these differences?
كيف يمكن للّغة أن تكون عاملا في وجود هذه الاختلافات؟
Let me tell you a little bit about how languages fundamentally differ.
دعوني أخبركم عن كيفيّة اختلاف اللّغات جوهريّا.
Linguists and cognitive scientists have been exploring this question for many years now.
لقد كان اللّغويون و خبراء علوم الادراك يبحثون في هذا السّؤال لسنوات.
And then I'll draw the connection between these two behaviors.
ثمّ سأقوم برسم الصّلة بين هاذين السّلوكين.
Many of you have probably already noticed that I'm Chinese.
العديد منكم لاحظ على الأرجح أنّني صينيّ.
I grew up in the Midwest of the United States.
ترعرعت في الغرب الأوسط الأمريكيّ.
And something I realized quite early on
و الأمر الذي أدركته مبكّرا كان هو أنّ
was that the Chinese language forced me to speak about and --
اللّغة الصينيّة أجبرتني على التّحدث عن --
in fact, more fundamentally than that --
في الواقع، الأمر أكثر جوهريّة من ذلك --
ever so slightly forced me to think about family in very different ways.
و التّفكير حول العائلة بطرق مختلفة.
Now, how might that be? Let me give you an example.
كيف يكون هذا ممكنا؟ دعوني أمدّكم بمثال.
Suppose I were talking with you and I was introducing you to my uncle.
لنفترض أنّني أتحدّث معكم و أحاول تقديمكم لقريبي.
You understood exactly what I just said in English.
لقد فهمتم بالضّبط ما قلته لتوّي بالانجليزية.
If we were speaking Mandarin Chinese with each other, though,
لكن إن كنّا نتحدّث معا باللّغة الصينية،
I wouldn't have that luxury.
لن يكون ذلك أمرا ممكنا.
I wouldn't have been able to convey so little information.
لن أتمكّن من ايصال مثل هذا القدر الصّغير من المعلومات.
What my language would have forced me to do,
ما قد تجبرني لغتي على القيام به،
instead of just telling you, "This is my uncle,"
هو أنّني عوض أن أقول:"هذا هو قريبي"،
is to tell you a tremendous amount of additional information.
سأخبركم بكمّ هائل من المعلومات الإضافيّة.
My language would force me to tell you
لغتني ستجبرني على أن أخبركم إن كان
whether or not this was an uncle on my mother's side or my father's side,
قريبي هذا من جهة الأم (خال) أو من جهة الأب (عمّ)،
whether this was an uncle by marriage or by birth,
إن كان قريبي بالزّواج أو بالولادة،
and if this man was my father's brother,
و إن كان قريبي هذا هو عميّ، عليّ أن أخبركم
whether he was older than or younger than my father.
إن كان أكبر سنّا أو أصغر من والدي.
All of this information is obligatory. Chinese doesn't let me ignore it.
كلّ هذه المعلومات ضروريّة. اللّغة الصينيّة لا تسمح لي بتجاهلها.
And in fact, if I want to speak correctly,
و بالواقع، إن أردت أن أتحدّث بطريقة سليمة،
Chinese forces me to constantly think about it.
فإنّ الصينيّة تجبرني على التّفكير دوما فيما أقوله.
Now, that fascinated me endlessly as a child,
لقد أبهرني ذلك عند صغري،
but what fascinates me even more today as an economist
لكن ما يبهرني أكثر اليوم كخبير اقتصاد،
is that some of these same differences carry through to how languages speak about time.
هو أنّ بعض هذه الاختلافات تصل إلى طريقة حديث هذه اللّغات عن الزّمن.
So for example, if I'm speaking in English, I have to speak grammatically differently
مثلا، إن كنت أتحدّث الانجليزية، أضطرّ للحديث بطرق مختلفة نحويّا
if I'm talking about past rain, "It rained yesterday,"
إن كنت أتحدّث في الماضي، أقول:"اقد أمطرت البارحة"،
current rain, "It is raining now,"
الآن، "إنّها تمطر"،
or future rain, "It will rain tomorrow."
و في المستقبل، "سوف تمطر غدا".
Notice that English requires a lot more information with respect to the timing of events.
لاحظوا أنّ الانجليزية تتطلّب أكثر معلومات مع تغيّر أوقات الأحداث.
Why? Because I have to consider that
لماذا؟ لأنّ علينا التّفكير في الأمر
and I have to modify what I'm saying to say, "It will rain," or "It's going to rain."
و أضطرّ لقول "ستمطر" أو "سوف تمطر".
It's simply not permissible in English to say, "It rain tomorrow."
لا يمكنني أن قول ببساطة:"هى مطر غدا".
In contrast to that, that's almost exactly what you would say in Chinese.
في المقابل، سيكون ذلك تماما ما تقوله إن كنت تتحدّث اللّغة الصينيّة.
A Chinese speaker can basically say something
النّاطق يالصينيّة يمكنه أن يقول شيئا
that sounds very strange to an English speaker's ears.
سيبدو في غاية الغرابة بالنّسبة لأذن النّاطق بالانجليزية.
They can say, "Yesterday it rain," "Now it rain," "Tomorrow it rain."
يمكنهم أن يقولوا:"البارحة تمطر"، "الآن تمطر"، "غدا تمطر".
In some deep sense, Chinese doesn't divide up the time spectrum
بصفة عامّة، الصينيّة لا تقوم بتقسيم الأطوار الزمنيّة
in the same way that English forces us to constantly do in order to speak correctly.
التي نضطّر للقيام بها إذا أردنا التّحدث بالانجليزية بطريقة سليمة.
Is this difference in languages
هل أنّ هذا الاختلاف في اللّغات
only between very, very distantly related languages, like English and Chinese?
موجود فقط في الّلغات البعيدة عن بعضها البعض، مثل الصينيّة و الانجليزية؟
Actually, no.
في الواقع، لا.
So many of you know, in this room, that English is a Germanic language.
العديد منكم بهذه الغرفة يعلمون أنّ الانجليزية لغة جرمانيّة.
What you may not have realized is that English is actually an outlier.
ما لا تعلمون هو أنّ الانجليزية شاذّة،
It is the only Germanic language that requires this.
إذ أنّها اللّغة الجرمانيّة الوحيدة التي تتطلّب هذا الأمر.
For example, most other Germanic language speakers
مثلا، معظم بقيّة المتحدّثين بلغات جرمانيّة
feel completely comfortable talking about rain tomorrow
لا يزعجهم أبدا الحديث عن المطر غدا بقول
by saying, "Morgen regnet es,"
"Morgen regnet es"
quite literally to an English ear, "It rain tomorrow."
التّرجمة الحرفيّة هي "تمطر غدا".
This led me, as a behavioral economist, to an intriguing hypothesis.
كخبير اقتصاد سلوكيّ، قادني هذا إلى فرضيّة مذهلة.
Could how you speak about time, could how your language forces you to think about time,
هل يمكن لطريقة تحدّثك عن الزّمن، هل يمكن عندما تجبرك لغتك أن تفكير حول الزّمن،
affect your propensity to behave across time?
أن تؤثّر في ميولك السلوكيّة عبر الزّمن؟
You speak English, a futured language.
أنتم تتحدّثون الانجليزية،
And what that means is that every time you discuss the future,
كلّ مرّة تقومون بالحديث عن المستقبل،
or any kind of a future event,
أو أيّ نوع من الأحداث المستقبليّة،
grammatically you're forced to cleave that from the present
نحويّا، فأنتم مجبرون على اشتقاق ذلك من المضارع
and treat it as if it's something viscerally different.
و التّعامل معه كما لو كان شيئا مختلفا جوهريّا.
Now suppose that that visceral difference
لنفترض أنّ هذا الاختلاف الجوهريّ
makes you subtly dissociate the future from the present every time you speak.
يجعلك تفصل الحاضر عن المستقبل ببراعة كلّ مرّة تتكلّم فيها.
If that's true and it makes the future feel
وإن كان هذا صحيحا، وكان المستقبل يبدو
like something more distant and more different from the present,
كأنّه شيء أبعد زمنيّا و أكثر اختلافا عن الحاضر،
that's going to make it harder to save.
هذا سيجعل توفير الأموال أمرا أصعب.
If, on the other hand, you speak a futureless language,
لكن من جهة أخرى، إن كنت تستعمل لغة لا مستقبل بها،
the present and the future, you speak about them identically.
متحدّثا عن الحاضر و المستقبل بالطّريقة نفسها.
If that subtly nudges you to feel about them identically,
إن كان ذلك دفعك إلى التّفكير فيهما بنفس الشّكل،
that's going to make it easier to save.
هذا سيجعل الادّخار أمرا أسهل.
Now this is a fanciful theory.
هذه تبدو نظريّة خياليّة.
I'm a professor, I get paid to have fanciful theories.
أنا بروفيسور، أتقاضى أموالا لكي أقوم بنظريات خياليّة.
But how would you actually go about testing such a theory?
لكن عمليّا، كيف يمكن تجربة مثل هذه النّظرية؟
Well, what I did with that was to access the linguistics literature.
حسنا، ما فعلته كان البحث في أدب الّلغويات .
And interestingly enough, there are pockets of futureless language speakers
الأمر المثير للاهتمام كان وجود العديد من اللّغات التي لا مستقبل بها
situated all over the world.
بمختلف أنحاء العالم.
This is a pocket of futureless language speakers in Northern Europe.
هذه مجموعة من شمال أوروبا من ناطقي اللّغات التي لا مستقبل بها.
Interestingly enough, when you start to crank the data,
الأمر المثير للاهتمام هو أنّه عند فحص هذه البيانات،
these pockets of futureless language speakers all around the world
هذه المجموعات من ناطقي اللّغات اللاّمستقبليّة حول أنحاء العالم
turn out to be, by and large, some of the world's best savers.
يتبيّن أنّها من أفضل الشعوب ادّخارا في العالم.
Just to give you a hint of that,
فقط لاعطائكم لمحة عن ذك،
let's look back at that OECD graph that we were talking about.
دعونا نفحص الرّسم البيانيّ لمنظمة التّعاون والتّنمية الاقتصادية الذي كنّا نتحدّث عنه.
What you see is that these bars are systematically taller
نرى أنّ هذه الخانات هي أطول منهجيّا
and systematically shifted to the left
و انتقلت إلى اليسار
compared to these bars which are the members of the OECD that speak futured languages.
مقارنة بالخانات التي تمثّل الدول العضوة بالمنظمة و التي تتكلّم لغات بها المستقبل.
What is the average difference here?
ماهو معدّل الاختلاف هنا؟
Five percentage points of your GDP saved per year.
توفير 5% من النّاتج الدّاخلي الخاّم سنويّا.
Over 25 years that has huge long-run effects on the wealth of your nation.
طيلة 25 سنة، يمكن لذلك أن يكون له تأثيرات ضخمة على المدى الطّويل على ثروات الأمّة.
Now while these findings are suggestive,
هذه الاكتشافات إيحائيّة،
countries can be different in so many different ways
قد تكون هناك عديد الاختلافات الأخرى بين هذه الدّول
that it's very, very difficult sometimes to account for all of these possible differences.
ومن الصّعب جدّا أخذ كلّ هذه الاختلافات الممكنة بعين الاعتبار.
What I'm going to show you, though, is something that I've been engaging in for a year,
لكن ما سأريكم الآن، هو أمر كنت منغمسا في القيام به طيلة سنة كاملة،
which is trying to gather all of the largest datasets
وهو محاولة جمع كلّ أكبر قواعد البيانات
that we have access to as economists,
التي لنا الحقّ في الحصول عليها كخبراء اقتصاد.
and I'm going to try and strip away all of those possible differences,
سأحاول فحص كلّ اختلاف ممكن،
hoping to get this relationship to break.
محاولا كسر هذه الصّلة.
And just in summary, no matter how far I push this, I can't get it to break.
الخلاصة أنّني مهما حاولت، لم أتمكّن من كسرها.
Let me show you how far you can do that.
دعوني أريكم إلى ايّ حدّ يمكننا الوصول.
One way to imagine that is I gather large datasets from around the world.
لتخيّل ذلك، جمعت أكبر القواعد البيانيّة من كلّ أنحاء العالم.
So for example, there is the Survey of Health, [Aging] and Retirement in Europe.
على سبيل المثال، هناك مسح للصّحة، الشّيخوخة و التّقاعد بأوروبا.
From this dataset you actually learn that retired European families
من هذه البيانات، يمكنك أن تعرف أنّ العائلات الأوروبيّة المتقاعدة
are extremely patient with survey takers.
كانت صبورة جدّا مع القائمين بالمسح.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So imagine that you're a retired household in Belgium and someone comes to your front door.
تخيّل أنّك متقاعد بمنزلك ببلجيكا، و أحدهم يدقّ بابك.
"Excuse me, would you mind if I peruse your stock portfolio?
"عفوا، هل تمانع إن قمت بتتبّع مجموعة أسهمك؟
Do you happen to know how much your house is worth? Do you mind telling me?
هل تعلم ما قيمة منزلك؟ هل تمانع إخباري؟
Would you happen to have a hallway that's more than 10 meters long?
هل هناك رواق بمنزلك يتجاوز طوله العشرة أمتار؟
If you do, would you mind if I timed how long it took you to walk down that hallway?
إن كان لديك، هل تمانع إن قمت بحساب المدّة التي تستغرقها لمروره؟
Would you mind squeezing as hard as you can, in your dominant hand, this device
هل تمانع الإمساك بيدك بهذه الأداة بأقصى قوّتك
so I can measure your grip strength?
كي أقول بقياس قوّة قبضتك؟
How about blowing into this tube so I can measure your lung capacity?"
ما رأيك في النّفخ عبر هذا الأنبوب حتّى أقيس قدرتك الرّئويّة؟"
The survey takes over a day.
هذا المسح يستغرق يوما كاملا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Combine that with a Demographic and Health Survey
نقوم بجمع ذلك مع المسح الدّيمغرافي و الصّحي الذي
collected by USAID in developing countries in Africa, for example,
قامت به الوكالة الأمريكية للتّنمية الدولية في الدّول النّامية الافريقيّة،
which that survey actually can go so far as to directly measure the HIV status
تمادى هذا المسح إلى قيامه بفحص وجود فيروس الايدز
of families living in, for example, rural Nigeria.
للعائلات التي تعيش مثلا في أرياف نيجيريا.
Combine that with a world value survey,
نجمع ذلك بمسح عالميّ،
which measures the political opinions and, fortunately for me, the savings behaviors
الذي قام بحساب الآراء السياسيّة، و لحسن حظّي، سلوكات الادّخار
of millions of families in hundreds of countries around the world.
لآلاف العائلات بمئات الدّول حول العالم.
Take all of that data, combine it, and this map is what you get.
نجمع كلّ هذه البيانات معا، و النّتيجة هي هذه الخريطة.
What you find is nine countries around the world
ما نجده هو 9 دول بالعالم
that have significant native populations
لها عدد كبير من السّكان الذين
which speak both futureless and futured languages.
يتحدّثون نوعيتي اللّغات التي بها و ليس بها مستقبل.
And what I'm going to do is form statistical matched pairs
سأقوم بتشكيل أزواج من البيانات المتماثلة
between families that are nearly identical on every dimension that I can measure,
بين العائات التي تتطابق تقريبا في كلّ الأبعاد التي يمكنني قياسها،
and then I'm going to explore whether or not the link between language and savings holds
ثمّ سأقوم باكتشاف ما إن كان هناك رابط بين اللّغة و سياسة الادّخار لديهم
even after controlling for all of these levels.
حتّى بعد حذف تأثيرات بقيّة الأبعاد الأخرى.
What are the characteristics we can control for?
ما هي الخاصّيات التي بامكاننا السيطرة عليها؟
Well I'm going to match families on country of birth and residence,
سأقوم بجمع العائلات حسب البلد الذي ولدوا فيه، و بلد الإقامة،
the demographics -- what sex, their age --
حسب معلومات ديموغرافيّة -- الجنس، السنّ --
their income level within their own country,
مستوى دخلهم في بلدهم،
their educational achievement, a lot about their family structure.
مستواهم التّعليمي، و الكثير حول تركيبة العائلة.
It turns out there are six different ways to be married in Europe.
اتّضح أنّ هناك 6 طرق مختلفة للزّواج في أوروبا.
And most granularly, I break them down by religion
قمت بتفصيلها حسب الدّين،
where there are 72 categories of religions in the world --
و على فكرة، هناك 72 صنفا من الأديان في العالم --
so an extreme level of granularity.
لذلك فإنّ مستوى التّفصيل كان متشدّدا.
There are 1.4 billion different ways that a family can find itself.
هناك 1.4 مليار طريقة مختلفة يمكن أن تكون عليها العائلة.
Now effectively everything I'm going to tell you from now on
كلّ ما سأقوله من هنا فصاعدا
is only comparing these basically nearly identical families.
يقارن فقط العائلات المتماثلة تقريبا.
It's getting as close as possible to the thought experiment
الأمر يقترب بشدّة من تلك التّجربة
of finding two families both of whom live in Brussels
حيث يتمّ إيجاد عائلتين تعيشان في بروكسيل
who are identical on every single one of these dimensions,
و تتطابقان في كلّ الأوجه، لكن
but one of whom speaks Flemish and one of whom speaks French;
أحدهما تتحدّث الهولنديّة و الأخرى تتحدّث الفرنسيّة؛
or two families that live in a rural district in Nigeria,
أو عائلتين تعيشان بريف نيجيريا
one of whom speaks Hausa and one of whom speaks Igbo.
و أحدهما تتحدّث اللّغة الهوسيّة، و الأخرى لغة الإغبو.
Now even after all of this granular level of control,
في هذه المرحلة من التّجزئة، هل يبدو أنّ
do futureless language speakers seem to save more?
ناطقي لغة ليس بها صيغة المستقبل قادرون على الادّخار أكثر؟
Yes, futureless language speakers, even after this level of control,
نعم، من يتكلّمون بلغة ليس بها صيغة المستقبل
are 30 percent more likely to report having saved in any given year.
لهم احتمال أن يدّخروا 30% أكثر من غيرهم في أيّ سنة.
Does this have cumulative effects?
هل لذلك تأثيرات تراكميّة؟
Yes, by the time they retire, futureless language speakers, holding constant their income,
نعم، عند قدوم وقت تقاعدهم، متحدّثو اللّغات التي ليس بها صيغة المستقبل
are going to retire with 25 percent more in savings.
سيتقاعدون مع 25% أكثر أموال بمدّخراتهم.
Can we push this data even further?
هل يمكننا دفع هذه البيانات إلى مستوى أعلى؟
Yes, because I just told you, we actually collect a lot of health data as economists.
نعم، كما أخبرتكم، نحن خبراء الاقتصاد نجمع البيانات الصحية.
Now how can we think about health behaviors to think about savings?
تتساءلون ما دخل البيانات الصحية في المدّخرات؟
Well, think about smoking, for example.
حسنا، فكّروا في التّدخين مثلا.
Smoking is in some deep sense negative savings.
التّدخين يمثّل ادّخارا سلبيّا نوعا ما.
If savings is current pain in exchange for future pleasure,
إن كان الادّخار ألما في الحاضر مقابل متعة في المستقبل،
smoking is just the opposite.
فإنّ التّدخين هو العكس تماما.
It's current pleasure in exchange for future pain.
هو متعة حاليّة مقابل ألم مستقبليّ.
What we should expect then is the opposite effect.
ما نتوقّعه إذن هو تأثير معاكس.
And that's exactly what we find.
وهو تماما ما نجد.
Futureless language speakers are 20 to 24 percent less likely
متحدّثو اللّغات التي ليست بها صيغة المستقبل لهم احتمال 20% إلى 40% أن
to be smoking at any given point in time compared to identical families,
يكونوا أقلّ تدخينا مقارنة بعائلات متطابقة معها،
and they're going to be 13 to 17 percent less likely
و سيكون لهم احتمال أقلّ ب13 إلى 17%
to be obese by the time they retire,
أن تصيبهم البدانة عند تقاعدهم،
and they're going to report being 21 percent more likely
وسيكونون لهم احتمال أكبر بـ21% أن يكونوا
to have used a condom in their last sexual encounter.
قد استعملوا واقيا ذكريّا أثناء آخر مرّة مارسوا فيها الجنس.
I could go on and on with the list of differences that you can find.
أستطيع المواصلة طويلا معدّدا الاختلافات الأخرى التي يمكنك إيجادها.
It's almost impossible not to find a savings behavior
إنّه تقريبا أمر مستحيل أن لا تجد سلوكا ادّخاريّا
for which this strong effect isn't present.
غير متأثّر بهذا العامل.
My linguistics and economics colleagues at Yale and I are just starting to do this work
أنا و زملائي من الاقتصاديين واللّغويّين بجامعة يال بدأنا لتوّنا هذا الأسبوع
and really explore and understand the ways that these subtle nudges
العمل على اكتشاف و فهم كيفيّة تأثير مثل هذه الضغوطات الصّغيرة
cause us to think more or less about the future every single time we speak.
على طريقة تفكيرنا بالمستقبل كلّ مرّة نتحدّث فيها.
Ultimately, the goal,
هدفنا النهائيّ هو،
once we understand how these subtle effects can change our decision making,
ما إن نفهم طريقة تأثير هذه الضّغوطات على القرارات التي نتّخذها،
we want to be able to provide people tools
نرغب في توفير وسائل للنّاس
so that they can consciously make themselves better savers
قادرة على جعلهم مدّخرين أفضل ادراكيّا
and more conscious investors in their own future.
و مستثمرين أكثر وعيا في المستقبل.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)